# **CURRICULUM VITAE**

# DR. (MRS.) OLIVER SHITANDA AMWAYI

Director, Quality Assurance

United States International University

Kasarani, off Thika Road P.O. Box 14634 - 00800 Nairobi, Kenya

3606393 (office) 0722828428 (cell)

0569776 (ID Number)

oamwayi@usiu.ac.ke or oamwayi@yahoo.com

# ACADEMIC QUALIFICATIONS

### 2007

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY IN EDUCATION
(Curriculum Studies)
CATHOLIC UNIVERSITY OF EATERN AFRICA, KENYA

### 2002

MASTER OF EDUCATION
(Curriculum Development)
KENYATTA UNIVERSITY, KENYA

#### 1997

BACHELOR OF EDUCATION

(Mathematics and Geography)

CATHOLIC UNIVERSITY OF EATERN AFRICA, KENYA

### PROFESSIONAL WORK EXPERIENCE

# **United States International University**

#### JANUARY 2015 - PRESENT

**Job Title: Director, Quality Assurance** 

## My Key Responsibilities:

- 1. Review and oversee the process of development and accreditation of new degree programs.
- 2. Plan and coordinate Program Assessment and Program Review across schools
- 3. Communicate with Deans and other relevant bodies in the university about any assessment/program review information that concerns their division.
- 4. Support other University departments to develop assessment of student learning outside the classroom.
- 5. Prepare and disseminate reports on the status of program assessment and program review in the various schools.
- 6. Plan and manage faculty training in Quality Assurance.
- 7. Prepare and disseminate reports on Quality Assurance activities.
- 8. Work with the Quality Assurance Committee to bring on board the entire campus on learning outcomes assessment requirements and the program review process.
- 9. Develop material to support the various Quality Assurance processes.
- 10. Set and meet clear goals and deadlines for the Quality Assurance process.
- 11. Conduct surveys on Quality Assurance matters.
- 12. Supervise and evaluate staff in the Quality Assurance Office.
- 13. Plan and manage departmental finances and other resources.
- 14. Represent the Quality Assurance department in various campus wide forums.
- 15. Represent the University in external quality assurance meetings as need may arise.
- 16. Oversee and prepare reports for the accreditation bodies.
- 17. Provide support in the preparation by the University for accreditation visits/inspections/audits.
- 18. Teach at least one class per year

**JULY 2010 – DECEMBER 2014** 

**Job Title: Curriculum Developer** 

My Key Responsibilities were:

1. Direct and provide technical support to schools intending to start new programs by

collaborating with Subject Matter Experts and the School Curriculum Development

Committee in the process of developing new programs to ensure that proposals meet

accreditation requirements.

2. Teach at least one course per semester to have classroom experience in teaching either

mathematics or research methods

3. Coordinate with the Associate DVC AA (QA) in the development of systems and procedures

that identify and define the operations of the quality assurance office in order to create

awareness and ensure efficiency of the office.

4. Coordinate with the Associate DVC AA (QA) in providing support to Faculty during course

and annual assessments, and review of programs to ensure that course/program is meeting

intended learning outcomes.

5. Schedule and conduct meetings/retreats related to Curriculum development.

6. Attend team meetings, training sessions and workshops of the QA Office.

7. Collaborate with the Institutional Research Office to develop research database that

incorporate current market trends related to programs on offer and those proposed. The

database may be utilized for justification of development of new programs and revision of

programs under review.

8. Perform other duties as assigned.

9. Offer service to profession and community through participation in the curriculum

development process as the need arises.

3

10. Participate in scholarship and professional improvement activities such as writing

papers/books; designing curriculum; attending conferences in the area of curriculum

development, and others.

**University of Nairobi** 

2006-June 2011

Part time lecturer, Taught Educational Statistics

**Kenya Technical Teachers College (K.T.T.C)** 

2001-July 2010

**Job Title: Senior Lecturer** 

Courses taught included Mathematics, Curriculum Development and Research Methods.

Supervised students' research projects

Assessed students during teaching practice

Oversaw the moderation of examinations in the Mathematics department

Mentored new lecturers in the Mathematics department

**Kabete High School** 

1987 – 1998

Taught Mathematics and Geography

Was a class teacher, a responsibility that enabled me to know students' needs, abilities and

interests better and acquire skills on how to guide and counsel the students.

Initiated the teaching of social education and ethics as an examinable subject.

4

### PROFESSIONAL SERVICE IN CRIME AND VIOLENCE PREVENTION TRAINING AND OTHERS

#### 1. CRIME AND VIOLENCE PREVENTION TRAINING

## **Background**

I have participated in the Crime and Violence Prevention Training (CVPT) program which began in 2011 when the Open Society Initiative for Eastern Africa (OSIEA), through its Crime and Violence Prevention Initiative, sponsored the first Crime and Violence Prevention Training. The program was implemented by United States International University - Africa (USIU-A) in collaboration with Kenya School of Government (KSG) in Kenya and later joined by the National Crime Research Centre (NCRC). The CVPT program has been designed to fill in identified gaps such as: The need to demystify crime, violence and victimization in the Kenyan context; a bias towards enforcement and control in dealing with crime and violence; the need to build broad based ownership of crime and violence prevention at all levels; etc.

The program continued to grow and expand and more partners have come on board to support it. For example, Coffey International agreed to partially fund the program. The project sponsored by OSIEA was successfully completed in December 2016. Recognizing the positive impact of the CVPT program on the participants and the need to reach out to more stakeholders, support was sought from the World Bank which has been funding the program since then. The programs come to a close in 2019.

#### Target group

The training targets current and future practitioners of crime prevention. This includes key national and county government officials (from a variety of ministries/departments including but not limited to internal security, the judiciary, **the national police service**, child and welfare, etc.) as well as representatives of non-state actors including the private sector, religious organizations, community groups, non-governmental organizations, academia, and the media.

### My role

I have played various roles in the Crime and Violence Prevention Training (CVPT) program as curriculum developer, coordinator, designer of assessments, and examiner. Additionally, I developed modules for the same.

#### 2. TRAINING OF TRAINERS

I have been a lead trainer in the Training of Trainers (TOT) of the following programmes

- a. Kenya Youth Empowerment and Opportunities Programme (KYEOP) TOT for Life Skills Trainers (16<sup>th</sup> – 20<sup>th</sup> September, 2019).
- Kenya Youth Empowerment and Opportunities Programme (KYEOP) TOT for Life Skills Trainers (18<sup>th</sup> – 22<sup>nd</sup> March, 2019).
- c. Kenya Youth Empowerment and Opportunities Programme (KYEOP) TOT for Life Skills Trainers (17<sup>th</sup> October, 2018).
- d. Crime and Violence Prevention Capacity Development Programme (15<sup>th</sup> 19<sup>th</sup> January, 2018).

# **RESEACH ACTIVITIES**

**2010:** Access and Equity: A Case Study of Free Primary Education in Kenya

**2007:** The Effects of Co-operative Learning on Mathematics Achievements and Attitudes of Secondary School Students in Kakamega District, Kenya. The results revealed that the co-operative learning strategy enhanced student's mathematics achievements and attitudes.

**18<sup>th</sup> March, 2006:** I participated in a USAID funded project "A Survey of Activities to Measure Learning Outcomes in Developing Countries" whose purpose was to inventory the assessment activities occurring in developing countries, which included Kenya.

**2002:** My master's thesis was entitled "Mastery of Euclidean Plane Geometry Concepts among Standard Seven Primary School Pupils: A Case of Kakamega Municipality (Kenya)". The purpose of the study was to investigate the mastery of Euclidean plane geometry by standard seven pupils and to find out whether there were any learning barriers that inhibited the pupils' mastery of the subject. The results of the study were quite informative.

PAPERS PRESENTED		
Title	Venue	Date
Approaches: Lessons from the	A Presentation at the 2 <sup>nd</sup> Biennial Conference on the State of Higher Education in Kenya at the Kenya School of Monetary Studies  [Sub-theme 2 (Round Table 2): Quality Assurance in Higher Education]	October 2, 2018
Mastery of Euclidean Plane Geometry Concepts Among Standard Seven Primary School Pupils: A Case of Kakamega Municipality		16 <sup>th</sup> October , 2002
Tests and Measurements in Training	Defense Staff College, Karen during the Directing Staff Appraisal Clinic	3 <sup>rd</sup> January, 2004
Tips on How to Improve on Mathematics Scores	ABC Mitaboni Girls' Secondary School	10 <sup>th</sup> July , 2005
HIV-AIDS: Women can make a difference	Catholic University of Eastern Africa Post-Graduate Conference	March, 2007

### PUBLICATIONS AND SCHOLARSHIP

Amwayi, O.S. (2011). Cooperative Learning: Effects on Mathematics Achievements and Attitudes. VDM Verlag Dr. Muller GmbH & Co. KG. Germany.

Amwayi, O. S. (2011). A Case Study of "Quality Matters: Free Primary Education in Kenya", submitted to UNESCO IBE to be used by TTCD for the second Diploma in Curriculum Design and Development.

#### STUDENT SUPERVISION

Christine A. Omondi (2019). Sustainable management of school meals programme for nonformal schools in Kibera slums. USIU

Franciscar Ndawa (2014). Factors that influence girl child access to primary school education:-A case of Mwitika division, Mutito district (kenya). USIU

**Referees:** Dr. (Mrs.) Adelheid Marie Bwire,

P.O. Box 30902-00200,

Nairobi.

Mob. No 0722804792

E-mail: addiemarie2010@gmail.com

Prof. Winston J. Akala University of Nairobi, School of Education, Department of Educational Administration and Planning P. O. Box 92, KIKUYU,

**KENYA** 

Cell Phone: 0723432546

E-mail: akala@uonbi.ac.ke or akalajumba@yahoo.com